Guide to the John Cage Papers, 1937 - 1992
John Cage Papers, 1937 - 1992
- Series 1. Manuscripts.
  - “Richard Lippold” (Folder 18-20)
    - Exhibition program, April 17-May 12, 1973. Programs for Richard Lippold Show at the Willard Gallery, New York featuring Cage’s poem.
  - “Listening to Music (Unpublished),” typescript, 7 p., 1937. (Folder 21)
  - “Looking at Painting from a Musical Point of View (Unpublished),” autograph manuscript, 6 p., n.d. (Folder 22)
  - M (Folder 23-25)
    - Corrected typescript and accompanying Wesleyan University Press correspondence, 1973-74.
    - Jacket art and corrected page mockup drawings, n.d.
    - Corrected printer’s proofs (blues), 1973.
  - “M Foreword” (Folder 26-29)
    - Autograph manuscript, 13 p., n.d.
    - Autograph manuscript, 20 p., n.d.
    - Corrected typescript, 9 p., n.d.
    - Annotated typescript, 8 p., n.d. Final draft.
    - Typescript, 8 p., n.d. Final draft. (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    - Notes, 1 p., n.d.
  - “M Front and Back Master” (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
    - Corrected typescript, 6 p., n.d.
    - Dust jackets, 5 copies.
  - “M Mesostics re and not re Duchamp” (Folder 5-6)
    - Corrected photocopy, 1 p., n.d. Dummy from Vogue (UK) with notes on verso.
    - Corrected photocopy, 1 p., after 1970. Notes and instructions for printer.
  - “M Mesostics re Merce Cunningham” (Folder 7-11)
    - Notebook, 12 p., March 1971. Contains 62 draft mesostics.
    - Notebook, 13 p., n.d. Notebook of mesostics and one loose page.
    - Notes, 39 p., n.d. Notes and calculations.
    - Corrected printouts, 25 p., n.d. Notes, mesostic drafts and calculations added to I Ching-based computer printouts.
    - Corrected typescript, 6 p., March 1971. Complete proof sheet with added numerical codes.
  - “M Press Reviews,” correspondence, clippings, and magazine issues, 1971-73. (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - “M Six Mesostics,” corrected typescripts, 3 p., n.d. (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - “Jackson MacLow (Something Else Press),” autograph and corrected typescripts, 2 p., n.d. Original folder reads “used for Stanzas for Iris Lezac.” (Folder 14)
  - “Manifestos and Dedication (Silence)” (Box 9, Folder 15-16)
    - Corrected typescript, 1 p., n.d. Printer’s instructions for Silence’s dedication page.
    - Corrected theater program, 16 p., March 2-May 18, 1951-52. Program for performances at The Living Theater. Includes “Manifesto” later included in Silence.
  - “McLuhan’s Influence,” corrected typescript, 2 p., Jan. 11, 1967. (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - “Mesostics (Miscellaneous),” autograph manuscripts and corrected typescripts, 11 p., 1970-73. (Folder 18)
  - “Miró (AYFM)” (Folder 19-22)
    - 2 notebooks, 12 p. each, n.d.
    - Autograph manuscripts, 3 p., n.d.
    - Corrected typescript, 5 p., n.d. Includes headnote.
    - Corrected typescript, 4 p., September 1966. Final draft. Includes headnote.
  - “Misc. Notes on Music and Dance (Unpublished),” Corrected typescripts and autograph manuscripts, 8 p., n.d. Drafts. (Folder 23)
  - “Mosaic (AYFM)” (Box 9, Folder 24-29)
    - Autograph manuscript, 17 p., n.d. Early draft.
    - Corrected typescript, 1 p., Sept. 1966. Draft of headnote.
    - Corrected typescript, 12 p., April 21, 1965. Includes a copy of “Mosaic” and a submission letter to David Madden, The Kenyon Review.
    - Notes, 12 p., n.d. Notes and calculations.
    - Notebooks, 2 steno pads, n.d.
    - Corrected typescript, 10 p., n.d. Final draft of essay. Includes headnote.
  - “Mureau” (Folder 30-32)
    - Steno pad, 60 p., n.d.
    - Corrected typescript, 21 p., Nov. 1970.
    - Magazine, 33 p., after April 1971. Copy of Misc [n.d.] in which “Mureau” appears.
  - “Mushroom Book (M)” (Box 10, Folder 1-4)
    - Autograph manuscripts, 18 p., n.d. 12 pages are laminated.
    - Autograph manuscripts and corrected typescripts, 6 p., n.d.
    - Typescript, 6 p., n.d. Photocopy of “Re and not re Fuller and Mao.”
    - Steno pad, 1972.
  - “Music and Films” (Folder 5-6)
    - Corrected typescripts, 3 p., after Jan. 1951. Draft of “A Few Ideas About Music and Films,” with notes to printer.
    - Magazine, Jan. 1951. Issue of Film Music Notes, including a corrected copy of “A Few Ideas About Music and Films.”
  - “A Music Lover’s Field Companion (Silence),” corrected typescript, 3 p., n.d. Includes headnote. (Folder 7)
  - “Nam June Paik (AYFM)” (Folder 8-11)
    - Notebook, n.d.
    - Corrected typescript, 4 p., Oct. 1965. Includes headnote.
    - Corrected typescript, 4 p., 1965. Final draft of essay. Includes headnote.
    - Exhibition catalog, 8 p., November 23 – December 11, 1965. Catalog for Nam June Paik show, Galeria Bonino, NY, in which “Nam June Paik: A Diary” was printed.
  - “Not Wanting to Say Anything About Marcel (8 Plexigrams, 2 Lithographs)” 6 steno notebooks, n.d. (Folder 12-17)
  - “Notations (Dustwrapper)” (Box 10, Folder 18-20)
    - Catalog, 78 p., 1973-74. Artist Books, Moore College of Art exhibition, March-April 1973, including Cage’s “Diary: How to Improve the World” and “Notations.”
    - Corrected typescript, 1 p., n.d.
    - Corrected typescript, 2 p., n.d.
  - Notebook, 1980. Pocket notebook includes annotated schedule to “Word of Mouth” lecture series, January 1980. (Folder 21)
  - “Lecture on Nothing (Silence)” Corrected typescript, 50 p., n.d. Includes headnote and afternote. (Audiocassette 22)
  - “Other People Think (Kostelanetz),” Corrected typescript, 4 p., n.d. (Folder 23)
  - “René Pomerleau,” notes, 3 p., n.d. (Folder 24)
  - “Problem (maybe published in Japan),” corrected typescript, 6 p., n.d. (Folder 25)
  - “Program Notes (not published in a book)” (Folder 26-30)
    - Corrected typescript, 3 p., n.d. Labeled “#A.”
    - Corrected typescript, 1 p., n.d. Labeled “#B,” “omit in favor of #A.”
    - Corrected typescript, 3 p., n.d. Labeled “#C.”
    - Typescript, 3 p., n.d.
    - Magazine clipping, n.d. Notes on verso.
  - “Rauschenberg (Kostelanetz),” autograph manuscript, 1 p., n.d. (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - “Rauschenberg (Silence),” corrected typescript, 16 p., Feb., 1961. Includes headnote. (Folder 32)
  - “Remarks before a Recital (Unpublished)” (Folder 33-37)
    - Notebook, n.d. Includes notes and drafts.
    - Corrected typescript, 5 p., n.d. Draft of remarks for a recital of David Tudor’s piano works.
    - Corrected typescript, 4 p., n.d.
    - Corrected typescript, 6 p., n.d. Includes headnote.
    - Corrected program, 2 p., March 19, 1959. “David Tudor,” La Maison Francaise at New York University.
  - “Remarks before a visit to Japan (Published in Sogetsu Program, Tokyo),” photocopied article, 1 p., Sept. 14, 1962. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - “Remarks on Winslow’s Music (Published in Wesleyan Cardinal)” (Folder 2-3)
    - Autograph manuscript, 9 p., Nov. 1960.
    - orrected typescript, 7 p., Nov. 1960. Includes note cards, one reading: “Do not use—too localized.”
  - “A Response to Lithgow’s Remarks (Unpublished)” (Folder 4-5)
    - Autograph manuscript, 2 p., Oct. 1961. Prepared for a panel discussion on “Art and Responsive Action,” Princeton NJ.
    - Typed letters signed, 2 p., October 7 and 9, 1961. Arrangements for speakers on panel.
  - “Rhythm Etc. (AYFM)” (Folder 6-7)
    - Autograph manuscripts and corrected typescripts, approximately 100 p., n.d. Notes and drafts.
    - Corrected typescript, 21 p., April 1962. Final draft of essay. Includes headnote and attached notes. Original folder reads: “To be published soon in G. Kere’s volume “Module” in series Vision + Value.”
  - “Richards, M.C.” (Folder 8-10)
    - Corrected typescripts, 9 p., n.d. Book review.
    - Uncorrected proofs, 2 p., n.d.
    - Cpy of published book review in Voice Literary Supplement, Dec. 27, 1973.
  - “Erik Satie (Silence)” (Folder 11-12)
    - Page layout sketch, 1 p., 1958.
    - Corrected typescript, 9 p., 1958. Includes headnote.
  - “Satie Controversy (Kostelanetz),” typed letter from Cage to Cecil Smith, 2 p., Nov. 22, 1950. (Folder 13)
  - Scores, 9 p., n.d. 9 typeset scores (1st page of each only) on newsprint with accompanying description of the piece. Includes: “Construction in Metal,” “Music for Carillon I,” “Concerto for Piano and Orchestra,” “Quartet: Twelve Tom Toms,” “Imaginary Landscape No. 1,” “Solo with Obbligato to the Accompaniment of 2 Voices in Canon,” “The Wonderful Widow of Eighteen Springs,” “Williams Mix,” and “She is Asleep.” (Folder 14)
  - “Seriously Comma (AYFM)” (Folder 15-16)
    - Autograph manuscript, 20 p., n.d.
    - Typescript, 5 p., September 1965. Final draft of essay. Includes headnote and note to printer. Original folder note: “To be published in French in a magazine.”
  - “Silence” (Folder 17-22)
    - Correspondence, 3 items, Sept.-Nov., 1961. Letters of congratulations on Silence’s publication.
    - Correspondence, 5 items, Sept.-Oct., 1961. Correspondence with Wesleyan University Press, including contract for Silence.
    - Correspondence, 2 pieces, 1961, 1967. Correspondence with M.I.T. Press and Andre Deutsch Limited. Includes 1967 M.I.T. Press sales figures.
    - Documents, 28 pieces, 1961-64. Copyright assignments and permissions granted to reproduce Cage’s essays in Silence.
    - Catalogs and book announcements, 7 items, 1961-67.
    - Catalogs and book announcements, 7 items, 1961-67.
    - Documents, approximately 100 p., ca. 1961-67. Reviews and announcements, clippings, 1961-67.
  - “Silence (Foreword)” (Box 11, Folder 23-24)
    - Corrected typescript, 8 p., n.d. Titled: “Notes for Recording (Folkways).”
    - Corrected typescript, 4 p., n.d. Final draft.
  - “Silence (Front Material),” 35 p., n.d. Layout designs and corrected proofs. (Folder 25)
  - Six Arts and Technology, corrected typescript, 3 p., n.d. (Folder 26)
    John Cage, writer: previously uncollected pieces, selected and introduced by Richard Kostelanetz. (New York: Limelight Editions, 1993).
  - “Sixty Replies to 30 Questions” (Folder 27-28)
    - 60 typed index cards, n.d.
    - Offprint, 1968. “Soixanté Résponses à Trente Questions de Daniel Charles” from Revue d’esthétique containing article.
  - “Lecture on Something (Silence)” (Folder 29-32)
    - Autogragh manuscript, 15 p., n.d.
    - Corrected typescript, 29 p., n.d. Includes headnote.
    - Corrected typescript, 8 p., n.d. Titled: “Title “Lecture on Something.” Performance copy.
    - Corrected typescript, 9 p., n.d. Performance copy on versos of Merce Cunningham Summer Course flyers.
  - “Songs (Song Books: Peters),” corrected typescript, 7 p., n.d. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - “Stories,” corrected typescripts and correspondence, 31 p., ca. 1966-67. (Folder 2)
    - Original folder note: “There are many duplicates here but I think they aren’t the stories in Silence.”
  - “Talk I (AYFM)” (Folder 3-4)
    - Corrected typescript, 3 p., n.d. Notes.
    - Corrected typescript, 7 p., September 1965. Final draft of text. Includes headnote.
  - “Tape Music (Unpublished)” (Folder 5-10)
    - Corrected typescript, 2 p., n.d. Titled: “Music for Magnetic Tape: Relation to the Field of Music.”
    - Corrected typescript, 2 p., n.d. Titled: “Music for Magnetic Tape: History.”
    - Corrected typescript, 2 p., n.d. Titled: “Music for Magnetic Tape: History.”
    - Corrected typescript, 6 p., n.d.
    - Corrected typescript, 1 p., n.d.
    - Corrected typescript, 1 p., n.d.
    - Corrected typescript, 11 p., n.d. Titled: “Dartmouth Spring 1955.”
  - “These Days (Kostelanetz)” (Folder 11-12)
    - Corrected typescript, 4 p., n.d.
    - Corrected photocopy of previous typescript, 4 p., 1968.
  - (Folder 13-14)
    - Typed letter, 1 p., January 26, 1972. To Ms. Elga Duval from Mimi Johnson, secretary to John Cage. Short note re: submission of a manuscript.
    - Typescript, 1 p., January 1972. Recollection of Dylan Thomas.
  - “Thomson (Original)” (Folder 15-16)
    - Corrected typescript, 185 p., spring 1956. Titled: “The Works of Virgil Thomson / A Study by John Cage.”
    - Autograph manuscript, 5 p., n.d. Notes.
  - “Music of Virgil Thomson,” corrected typescript, 251 p., n.d. Later draft of “The Works of Virgil Thomson.” (Folder 17)
  - “Tobey (Published in Barol Catalog),” typescript, 2 p., n.d. Recollections of Mark Tobey.“Tobey (Published in Barol Catalog),” typescript, 2 p., n.d. Recollections of Mark Tobey. (Folder 18)
  - “University in Motion (Unpublished),” corrected typescript, 3 p., n.d. Titled: “University in Motion: Matrix for the Arts.” (Folder 19)
  - “Edgard Varèse (Silence),” corrected typescript, 3 p., September 23, 1958. Published in Nutida Musik (Stockholm), Fall 1958. Includes headnote. (Folder 20)
  - Varèse, corrected typescript, 2 p., after 1972. Book review by Cage of Louise Varèse, Varèse, W. W. Norton, 1972. (Folder 21)
  - Variations III (Unpublished),” corrected typescript, 1 p., n.d. Original folder note: “Written during Berlin performance.” (Folder 22)
  - “Wesleyan Papers (Misc., Unpublished)” (Folder 23-26)
    - Corrected typescript, 4 p., n.d. Titled: “Statement on Fellowship in the Wesleyan Center for Advanced Studies (1960-1961).”
    - Cage’s fellowship report.
    - Autograph manuscript, 1 p., n.d. Notes.
    - Corrected typescript, 9 p., n.d. Titled: “Gentlemen of the Wesleyan Glee Club.” Address to the Wesleyan Glee Club.
    - Typescript, 6 p., summer 1963. Proposal by Cage and David Tudor for Wesleyan to establish a Center for Experimental Music.
  - “What Are We Eating?” (Folder 27-29)
    - Steno pad, n.d. Titled: “What Are We Eating? And What Are We Eating? (38 Variations on a Theme by Alison Knowles).”
    - Steno pad, n.d. Labeled: “I.” Includes four loose sheets of notes.
    - Steno pad, n.d. Labeled: “II.”
  - “Where Are We Going? and What [Are We Doing?] (Silence)” (Box 13, Folder 1-6)
    - Photocopied letter, 2 p., n.d. From Cage to Wesleyan University Press commenting on “Where Are We Going? and What Are We Doing?”
    - Steno pad, n.d.
    - Steno pad, n.d. Labeled: “I / Blue / 933.”
    - Steno pad, n.d. Labeled: “II / Green / 926.”
    - Steno pad, n.d. Labeled: “III / Red / 848.”
    - Steno pad, n.d. Labeled: “IV / Orange / 914.”
  - “Where Are We Going? etc. (Silence)” (Folder 7-10)
    - Autograph manuscript, 3 p., n.d. Draft of headnote.
    - Autograph manuscript, 1 p., n.d. Notes.
    - Autograph manuscript, 2 p., n.d. Notes.
    - Corrected typescript, 90 p., April 26, 1961. Complete draft of “Where Are We Going? and What Are We Doing?” with headnote.
  - “Where Do We Go From Here? (A Year From Monday)” (Folder 11-14)
    - Corrected typescript, 12 p., n.d. Originally titled “From a Starting Point.”
    - Typescript, 8 p., n.d. Final draft. Includes headnote.
    - Corrected typescript, 9 p., 1963. Final draft of essay. Includes headnote, notes to printer, and printer’s corrections.
    - Magazine, 1963. Copy of Dance Perspectives 16 in which the essay was published.
  - “A Year From Monday” (Folder 15-16)
    - Book production documents, 6 items, 1966-68. Includes: original contract for A Year From Monday, July 18, 1966; letter to from J.R. de la Torre Bueno [Wesleyan University Press] regarding recent copyright assignments, February 21, 1968; three copyright assignments from various magazines; and press release from Wesleyan University Press.
    - Book reviews, approximately 50 items, 1966-68.
  - “Year From Monday (Afterword)” (Folder 17-18)
    - Steno pad, n.d.
    - Corrected typescript, 22 p., n.d. Drafts.
  - Corrected typescript, 7 p., n.d. (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
    - Corrected typescript, 6 p., n.d. Later draft.
    - Corrected proofs, 2 p., n.d.
  - “Year From Monday (Foreward)” (Box 14, Folder 4-5)
    - Corrected typescript, 3 p., n.d.
    - Corrected typescript, 3 p., October 1966.
  - “Year From Monday (Headnotes)” (Box 14, Folder 6-11)
    - Steno pad, n.d.
    - Corrected typescript, 1 p., spring 1966. Titled: “Materials by John Cage submitted spring 1966 for next book.”
    - Corrected typescript, 1 p., August 15, 1966. Titled: “Contents.” Proposed table of contents for AYFM.
    - Corrected typescript, 1 p., n.d. Titled: “Headnote: Talk I.”
    - Corrected typescript, 1 p., n.d. Titled: “Headnote: Emma Lake.”
    - Corrected typescript, 1 p., n.d. Titled: “Headnote: Emma Lake.”
    - Corrected typescript, 1 p., December 15, 1966. Titled: “Contents and Status, as of 12/15/66.”
  - Memberships and Correspondence (3 pieces), 1980, 1991-92 (Folder 12)
- Series 2. Interviews with Cage.
  - Barbarber 51 Amsterdam, Een interview met John Cage Door Michael Kirby en Richard Schechner, March 1967 (Dutch) (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Revue d'Esthetique, "Soixante réponses à trente questions de Daniel Charles" (Sixty Answers to thirty questions of Daniel Charles), 1968 (French)
  - North American Review, Things to Do: An Interview with John Cage, winter 1969
  - Coast FM and Fine Arts, John Cage: Dean of the Musical Avant-Garde, by Genevieve Marcus, March 1970 (Folder 2)
  - Royal Albert Hall Concert Program and Interview, John Cage and David Tudor 22 May 1972
  - Prolog vol. 19/20 Zagreb, Razgovor sa Johnom Cageom: zivot koji postaje umtjetnost, 1974 (Serbo-Croatian)
  - New York Arts Journal, John Cage on his music May 1976
  - View, Interviews with Robin White, Vol. 1 1978-1979 (Folder 3)
  - Community Arts Newsletter, John Cage: Interview, by Joshua Harrison, February 1980 (Folder 4)
  - Performance, No. 7, John Cage and Merce Cunningham in London, 1980
  - Conversation without Feldman (Cage and Geoffrey Barnard), Black Ram Books, 1980
  - Musicworks, No. 17, A Conversation with John Cage, Fall 1981
  - Res 6, Cage: Conversation with Morton Feldman, Autumn 1983 (Folder 5)
  - Issues Monthley, Music Without Bars: An Interview with John Cage, by Olivia Birkelund and Alex Sichel, November 1984
  - Pratt Journal of Architecture, Architecture and Abstraction, An Interview with John Cage, Fall 1985
  - Res 10, Cage: On Collaboration in Art, a conversation with David Shapiro, Autumn 1985
  - Minneapolis City Pages, Interview: New Music Pioneer John Cage on art, politics and mushrooms, by Steve A. Kvaal October 23, 1985
  - Il Gionale della Musica, John Cage si racconta, September 1987 (Italian) (Folder 6)
  - Art Meets Science and Spirituality in a Changing Economy (conference); John Cage Interview, 7 September 1989, San Francisco
  - The Print Collector's Newsletter, John Cage: An Interview, by Vincent Katz, Vol XX No. 6, January-February 1990
  - Tricycle: The Buddhist Review, Taking Chances: Laurie Anderson Talks with John Cage, Summer 1992 (Laurie Anderson and Cage)
  - CONNECTION (ND) (Folder 7)
  - Cage/Hans G. Helms (ND, German and English)
  - Irving Sandler and Cage (ND, transcript with corrections)
  - Cage Interview, Cage/(Larry?) Austin (ND)
  - Conversations with John Cage/Christian Wolff, Hans G. Helms (ND, German and English)
- Series 3. Fan Mail and Mail Art.
  - 3A. Fan Mail Without Enclosures (Box 16)
  - 3B. Fan Mail With Enclosures (Box 17-23)
    The fan mail with enclosures is not currently arranged in a particular order, but some highlights are noted below.
  - Dick Higgins (Poetry Project) Expressionist Manifesto MS (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Invitation to Andy Warhol Memorial Service (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Portuguese Composer Augusto de Campos, Poetamenos (Songs) dedicated to Cage, 1973 (Folder 3)
  - Delhi and New Delhi Guide, road map of India, 1964 (Folder 5)
  - Assorted print materials associated with Buckminster Fuller projects (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Assorted print materials by literary scholar Ihab Hassin with notes from Author to Cage (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Marshall McLuhan, "The Future of Film in Canada" MS, 1964
  - Living Theater Press Folder w/ note from founder Judith Molina to Cage, 1989 (Folder 2)
  - Letter from Dick Higgins [Fluxus pioneer and poet] with poems, 1960 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Portrait of John Cage, assemblage by Mary Francis Judge, 1972
  - Letter from James Turrell and photos of Roden Crater Project, 1984
  - Grinning Idiot Salutes Modern Dance,; article on William de Kooning and Black Mountain College with notes, 1984
  - Fletcher Copp National Poetry Week "Poem a Day" envelope (Folder 6)
  - Bad News comics periodical featuring Indeterminacy, a comic featuring Cage as title character (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - "What I am Trying to Do" by Buckminster Fuller, MS addressed to Cage by author along side several other print articles signed by Fuller to Cage
  - Gallery guide to "Nam June Paik: Electronic Art," Galeria Bonino, New York City, 1965
  - Saturday Review 1 April 1967 cover article "Is Man Changing the Climate of the Earth?," cover photo of Fuller, with signed dedication from Fuller to Cage
  - Material regarding NEA funding controversy of early 1990s (Folder 2)
  - Photograph proofs of a Cage lecture, 1987 (Box 23, Folder 4)
- Series 4. Cage Ephemera.
  - Events, Programs, Brochures (Box 24)
  - Books or Parts of Books about Cage (Box 25-26)
  - Dedications, Honors, Related Items (Box 27-28)
  - Books about Cage (Box 29)
  - Art Exhibition Catalogs including Work by Cage
  - Publisher's Catalogs